the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform I'm Dr Andy Galpin a professor
of Kinesiology in the center for sport
performance at Cal State Fullerton in
the center our mission is to conduct and
disseminate research that enhances human
performance in addition to my role as a
scientist I also work directly with high
performing athletes this could include
Olympic gold medalists world champions
MVPs SI young winners Allstars a Ross
multiple Sports the NHL NBA the NFL PGA
Tour boxing the UFC and many more so
while I focus most of my career on Sport
and athletes specifically my real
passion is the physiology behind that
and so what I hope to share with you
over this podcast is a deep dive into
the physiology of human performance now
that doesn't necessarily mean Sports per
se this is really human performance at
its finest most broadest definition this
could be athletes musicians leaders
scientists Educators or anything else in
between human performance really is what
you want your body to be capable of so
in order to accomplish that I'm
extremely excited to share with you the
physiology behind human performance in a
way that is engaging applicable and most
importantly useful today we're going to
be talking about muscle more
specifically skeletal muscle my favorite
now I know when you first hear that your
mind May jump to things like sport
performance and big giant muscles and
bodybuilding and Aesthetics and while
that may or may not be of interest to
you I will tell you candidly it's a
large interest of mine you may be
surprised to learn that muscle quality
and quantity are incredibly important
for your overall health and well-being
yeah you heard that right quality muscle
is essential for the Vitality of nearly
every cell organ or organ system in your
entire body let me give you two specific
examples of what I'm talking about first
is the connection between muscle and the
Brain
now there are many lines of evidence we
could utilize here but one that I think
highlights the point beautifully is a
recent study on about a half a million
participants mostly middle-aged men and
women and in that they found that about
30% of dementia cases were directly
attributable to low grip strength now
that may sound alarming and or
interesting to you and I promise we'll
get into the details of that study and
many others later in the show now that
was an example of muscle quality or
functionality let me give you another
one regarding muscle quantity or size
and how that will directly relate to
longevity or lifespan once again there's
lots of research to pull from and we'll
get into this later in the show but it's
very clear that being under muscled is a
significant problem in fact we know this
is such a big problem the National
Institute of Health has an entire Wing
dedicated specifically to sarcopenia
which is the advanced loss of muscle
with age if you'd like some hard numbers
to wrap your head around a little bit
here consider this those in the bottom
20th perc versus the top 20 percentile
in terms of how much muscle mass you
have on your entire body well those in
the bottom portion have about two times
the risk of all cause mortality as those
in the top and so while we certainly are
going to consider functionality or
quality most important quantity matters
a lot as well so based upon what I've
just shared and more that we'll get into
later in the show to me skeleton muscle
is by far the most important organ in
your entire body now in order to
convince you of that I'm going to start
by telling you how it actually regulates
performance across the entire system
this includes everything from its
relationship to how long and how well
you're going to live to how it regulates
your blood glucose metabolism and
overall energy production to other
factors that you may or may not also be
aware of after that we'll get into what
muscle actually is how is the structure
and the function of it determining how
you move throughout the world and then
finally we'll get into the assessment
piece how do you identify whether or not
you have enough muscle and if you don't
how do you go about improving that now
before we go too much further I'd like
to take a quick break and thank our
sponsors because they make this show
possible not only are they on this list
because they offer great products and
services but because I actually
personally love them and use them myself
today's episode is brought to you by
absolute rest sleep is the Bedrock of
human performance which is why I always
focus on it with my Elite athletes but
despite trying every wearable and even
sending people people to full-blown
clinical testing in sleep Labs we rarely
got very far that's why 2 years ago I
co-founded absolute rest which redefines
what it means to be a high performance
sleeper after tremendous success we are
now ready for our next challenge a
firstof its kind sleep optimization
program that combines Advanced sleep
technology with personalized coaching
all at a fraction of the cost of a
traditional sleep study the Sleep lens
program allows you to run a full FDA
approved clinical grade sleep study from
your fingertip every single night our
team of sleep scientists then use your
data to create personalized solutions
that drive real changes in your sleep no
more overnight stays in creepy sleep
Labs no more wearables with questionable
accuracy and no more wondering if the
changes you're making in your nightly
routine habits or supplements are
actually working or not if you'd like to
try absolute rest go to Absolut rest.com
for/ perform to secure your spot in the
Sleep lens program and save $100 that's
Absolut rest.com / perform today's
episode is also brought to you by
momentus momentus makes safe highquality
supplements now I naturally despise and
frankly don't trust most supplement
companies and for good reason in fact I
recently co-authored a review article
that was published in 20123 in which we
found that the amount of adulterations
which are accidental contaminants or
deliberate spiking like adding
stimulants or anabolic or other agents
which are not supposed to be in the
product or mislabeling is shockingly
high
range from about 10 to 40% of all
supplements depending on the study that
you pulled so I actually honestly spent
literally years vetting both momentus
and their leadership team before
deciding to officially partner with them
last year every single momentus product
is thirdparty tested and that's
expensive and many are even further NSF
certified for sport but more unique than
that is their vision for the future of
where this frankly dysfunctional
industry should go on top of this strong
ethical company value their products are
also fantastic they're used by the best
of the best including countless
professional teams Olympic committees 31
of the 32 NFL teams many members of the
Department of Defense and many more they
offer a range of products for me those
are your creatine vitamin D and fish
oils now none of you have to use
supplements and I genuinely hope you
never feel pressured to do so if you
don't want to however they can be
beneficial to some so if you're going to
use them I strongly encourage choosing a
brand like momentus which in my opinion
has the highest safety and quality
standards in the world if you'd like to
give momentus a try go to
live.com perform to get 20% off your
order again that's lives.com
perform to get 20% off okay so why do I
think skeletal muscle is so special well
I want to break this into two parts the
first is the quantity of muscle you have
and the second is quality now the
quantity of muscle compared to other
organ systems say your immune system
your brain central nervous system or
even like your bones skeletal muscle is
the one you have the most control over
with lifestyle factors so what I mean by
that is it is the one you can manipulate
the most to alter your physical
appearance now you may want to look a
certain way or not another way that's
entirely up to you but skeleton muscle
is the place you will go to determine
that of course you can reduce the amount
of body fat you have overall with
lifestyle but it's hard to really pick
that from a certain space or place on
your body for example if you wanted to
lose fat on your triceps or the back of
your arm or on your legs or so it's
really difficult to Target the fat loss
in that area it tends to come globally a
little bit from everywhere in your body
but skeletal muscle is different you can
absolutely Focus entirely on growing
your calves or on one arm relative to
the other or anything else you want to
do so again of all of the different
organ systems and structures on your
body it is the one you have the most
control over to determine how you
look that said I want to focus more on
the second part of our discussion here
which is the quality of the muscle so
the functionality what it's providing to
your body and how it's helping you
navigate through the world so remember
skeletal muscle is the direct interface
with the world I know folks that are in
the Neuroscience Department people like
Andrew love to give all the credit to
the nervous system and the brain and
that's fine obviously that's what's
making the decisions but skeletal muscle
is the Workhorse so nothing will
actually get accomplished without the
skeletal muscle it's a little bit of
chicken and egg here I get that but in
my opinion nothing is going to happen in
your body healthwise or actual again
interfacing with the world without
skeletal muscle this is the Workhorse of
your life now before we go too much
further I want to back up just a touch I
realize I've described skeletal muscle
as an organ system several times now and
many of you may not know what that means
or why it matters you see if you would
have gone on something like Jeopardy in
in 1990 and they asked a question of
what's the biggest organ in your body
you would have probably said skin and
that would have been correct at the time
however hopefully jeopardies made a
change we realize that's not the correct
answer it is skeletal muscle by a
landslide so what it means to be an
organ is that it secretes something and
communicates to other parts of your body
and it wasn't really until the last 20
years where scientists have identified
and realized that skeletal muscle is
what we would say not stupid in other
words we used to again neuroscientists
think that skeletal muscle just is a
one-way Street information comes in from
the nervous system tells muscle what to
do and then it executes well we now
realize skeletal muscle is far smarter
than that it is not only accepting
information from the nervous system also
from the hormones the endocrine system
things that are in your blood and
everywhere else it's also sending
signals back out this includes things
that are now called exines so these are
cyto or again other information
molecules excreted from muscle in this
case in response specifically to
exercise and their direct Target is
other organ systems in the body this
would include the kidneys liver lungs
brain and every other part of your
system there are also other molecules
that we'll discuss later such as
non-coding mrnas that are critical to
your body understanding its overall
status you see really the way that I
think about it is skeletal muscle given
the fact that it occupies far more space
in your body than anything else is the
primary key to physiology communication
it is the biggest factor that is both
receiving and extending information out
to the rest of your body so when you
don't have enough of it or it is
compromised you're going to see problems
in every other area of your life to
double down on that statement if you
were to look across the literature on
both skeletal muscle mass as well as
muscle quality
so think in this case muscle power
muscle strength or something like that
you will see connections to basically
every aspect of overall human health and
performance this is why if you were to
look into the scientific literature on
everything from sport performance to all
CA mortality you'll see a strong tie to
skeletal muscle quantity and quality so
for example skeletal muscle has been
implicated in the regulation of numerous
systems which include but are not
limited to all cause morbidity and
mortality cardiovascular health
cognitive Health brain health mood
inflammation immunity fertility
metabolic Health Hormone Health bone
health and much more another important
thing to realize is that most of your
metabolism in your body is actually
occurring in your skeletal muscle in
fact because of this around 85% or so of
the heat you generate in your body is
coming from skeletal muscle it's also
the primary place in which you dispose
of and regulate blood glucose which is
important for both short-term
performance as well as long-term Health
in fact Recent research has shown that
athletes are up to 25% more effective at
disposing glucose into their muscle than
non-athletes so regardless of how you're
defining Human Performance whether that
be hit a golf ball 300 yards fix your
low back pain have more focus at work or
alter how you physically appear skeletal
muscle is going to be at the center of
that conversation so how much can really
change let's talk about the adaptability
or what we call plasticity of skeletal
muscle in my opinion I judge the overall
quality of skeletal muscle in three main
areas effectively you can think of these
three as look good feel good and play
good what that means for everyone the
first one is pretty obvious it should
look how you want it to look and that's
going to be different for everyone
people want different sizes and shapes
some folks want more size than certain
muscles and muscle groups and less than
others that's entire enely up to you the
second one Feelgood this should be
resilient and non-sensitive so you
should be able to engage in multiple
types of metabolic processes should be
able to handle multiple types of
contractions and multiple ranges of
motion Etc so again we want resilient
muscle that can do many things basically
on demand the last one then is Play Good
can we execute on the things we're
asking it to do so can it go fast when
we want it to go fast can it go under
control when we want it to be under
control can it be High Precision can it
be gross movement and can it respond and
recover quickly so as we continue on
this discussion I'm going to have all
three of those goals in mind that really
at the end of the day it should look a
certain way it should be resilient be
able to do many things in many areas but
then also be able to execute the exact
way that you personally want it to
execute as a quick example when we say
smooth muscle think about the tiny
muscles involved in digestion moving
food throughout your digestive tract
stuff that is really not own your
voluntary control not really going to
respond and change say growing in size
increasing in strength and responds to a
workout or lifestyle interventions it's
kind of the stuff that moves your life
beyond your sematic or cognitive control
now in terms of cardiac we're really
basically talking about one thing and
that's your heart there's a few other
things that go along with that but
that's basically what we're talking
about skeletal muscle is almost
everything else so it is your biceps
muscles your hamstring muscles your
quadriceps the things that you have both
voluntary and involuntary control over
they tend to be large muscles but they
can be the small ones as well think of
your intercostals the muscles between
your ribs that are contracted to expand
your chest so that you can breathe and
bring volume into your lungs uh the
small muscles in your eye that control
fine motor movement and everything else
like that so to recap smooth muscle is
the stuff you have very little control
over tends to be the muscles necessary
to keep you alive for digestion and
breathing and things like that cardiac
is effectively your heart and then
skeletal muscle is basically everything
else it's the stuff that relegates human
movement you have both control and
involuntary control of it they can be
large muscles or small muscles but once
again it's basically everything non-s
smooth and non-cardiac now if you've
listened to any of Dr Andrew Herman's
work he's talked extensively about the
role of neuroplasticity which is the
ability of your nervous system to adapt
or change in response to various stimuli
or lack there up well skeletal muscle
ability to respond like that is even
greater so it will change its nature in
both the short term and now we're
talking in order of seconds to minutes
as well as in the long term so its
ability to alter how you feel and
perform is extensive in order to
understand that we need to talk briefly
about what muscle really is so what
exactly is skeletal muscle well let's
start all the way back at the beginning
in your body you've got somewhere
between 6 to 700 different muscles now
we don't know the exact number there's
no scientific consensus on that in fact
I remember fairly recently a paper came
out arguing for the identification of a
fifth quadricep muscle so the tradition
is that you've got four hence quadricep
muscles in your your quad or your thigh
there and they had argued that they had
identified a fifth one now I don't know
the literature on that as well anymore
but the point is you've got a large
number of muscles throughout your entire
body we tend to group them into muscle
groups so continuing with the quadriceps
theme we tend to call that the quad
muscles although that has actually Four
individual muscles your biceps are
actually a combination of several
different biceps muscles your triceps
etc etc and so we've got all the muscles
in our body we've got these subgrouping
of muscle groups and then within each
individual muscle you have hundreds of
thousands of muscle fibers think of this
like a ponytail so while you'd call that
ponytail one thing it's actually just
comprised of thousands of different
individual hairs so when we want to talk
about the individual hair we say hair
follicule if we want to talk about the
ponytail as a unit we say the ponytail
so the same thing would happen I could
talk about your hamstring muscles but
really am I talking about one muscle the
say the semimembranosus or
semitendinosis the hamstrings as a group
or the individual fibers within each of
those individual
muscles so drilling down on that if you
can imagine going back to the ponytail
there is a layer of connective tissue or
fascia that surrounds each of these
muscle fibers that holds them together
but that's what actually collectively
makes them one unit and why we call that
a muscle that muscle is then wrapped
around further with more connected
tissue all that comes together to form a
tendon that tendon then connects the
bone such that when you activate or
contract any of those muscle fibers it
contracts the muscle as a whole tends to
contract the entire muscle group that
entire muscle group comes together goes
into a tendon that tendon then pulls the
bone so the easy example again sticking
with the quads is an easy theme you
contract any of the muscle fibers within
say the vasis lateralis the muscle that
is on the far outside of your leg that
is one of the quadricep muscles the
entire quad tends to feel like it's
Contracting that then goes over through
the Patell Tenon the Patell Tenon
inserts on the front of the lower leg
bone which causes the lower leg bone to
lift up and for your lower leg to extend
that quickly is how muscles work and how
they actually cause human movement it's
through one the activation of the muscle
two the contraction of the muscle and
then three the muscle pulling on
connective tissue which makes bones move
now the amount of muscle fibers you've
got in each muscle varies pretty highly
and it's somewhere in the neighborhood
of 1 to 300,000 individual fibers
interestingly this number will double
during the first few months of your life
and then basically stabilize by the time
you reach adulthood now as I mentioned
you've got somewhere between 100 and
300,000 fibers
per muscle one example the biceps brachi
has been shown to have about 250,000
muscle fibers and so if you ran some
quick math there that would mean most of
us probably have somewhere in the
neighborhood of between 125 to 250
million muscle fibers throughout our
entire body and these fibers are
extraordinarily unique in all of biology
for a couple of reasons number one they
are absolutely huge they are some of the
biggest cells by volume in all of
biology it is common to have a muscle
fiber that is up to 2 to 3 cm long
and in fact many have been shown to be
up to 10 cm or so long um think about
the sartorious muscle this muscle that
goes from kind of the inside of your
hipbone that front side there and goes
all the the inside of your knee it is
theorized and some folks will say in
physiology Lord that you can have a
single muscle fiber that runs the entire
length of that I don't actually know
whether or not that's true but it would
not be rare to see a fiber that is again
four to five up to 6 in Long which is
enormous in terms of the width same kind
of idea you'll see these things as
extremely large right somewhere between
four to five micrometers in terms of
cross-sectional areas micrometer squared
to give you a little bit of concept of
how big that is number one you can see
that with a naked eye I could pull up in
my laboratory a pair of tweezers a
single muscle fiber from a human I could
hold it up right now and on this camera
you would absolutely be able to see that
both on camera as well as with your
naked eye if you were within even you
know 5 to 10 ft of me in terms of
cross-sectional area you're looking at
something like 4 to 5,000 micrometers
squared which a little bit of context
there uh one time actually I had a long
established powerlifter as well as
anabolic steroid user in my lab and we
biopsied this individual and his muscle
fibers were closer to
9,000 and the closest equivalent we
found there was actually rhinoceros so
muscle fibers are not only large in
terms of biology but the ability to gain
size is extraordinary as again I said
earlier one of the things that makes
skeletal muscle in humans especially
unique is the ability to respond and
adapt based on stimuli in fact it seems
to be quite unending now we'll come back
and talk about muscle fiber size and how
to develop it a little bit later but
getting back to this idea of fiber
number as I mentioned it's not to be
fairly fixed once you reach adulthood
however it is extremely clear that this
number will go down with aging unless
you do something proactively to prevent
that it's actually also very clear that
this number can increase with anabolic
steroid use now this concept of growing
new muscle fibers is called hyperplasia
and something that has been hotly
contested in the exercise physiology
world for many many decades now I will
give you a little bit of a behind the
scenes here I personally am always been
a big believer in hyperplasia happening
I won't say the science is strongly in
my support but it's when one of the
passion projects that that I'm not going
to give up on okay now what I'm really
talking about here is there's no
question whatsoever that new cells can
grow that's not really the debate what
is up for discussion though is whether
or not that happens as a normal response
to normal training in healthy
humans there is strong evidence that
anabolic steroid use especially over a
number of years can increase that number
and again we know it will decrease with
aging now when I say anabolic steroid
use I'm mostly talking about
testosterone here now please so I can be
ultra clear here I am not encouraging
anyone to utilize antibiotic steroids or
test testosterone I'm not a medical
doctor if you are interested in any use
of exogenous hormones that's something
you need to work out with your personal
position this is not again me
encouraging or recommending those use I
will not also suggest it will make your
muscle healthier or any better there are
many factors to think about when
considering exogenous hormones and I not
the person to take advice from on those
things we also know that consistent
strength training will prevent the loss
of those muscle fibers over time
whether or not you can again go above
and beyond your normal set at a normal
age with just basic strength training I
guess is still up for debate there are
maybe some things if you catch me off
camera I'm willing to share with you but
according to the current science right
now that's the best we can say so what
this means is you've got two paths to
changing skeletal muscle structure and
function the first is increasing the
amount of muscle fibers as we just got
done discussing that's probably quite
challenging to do in normal settings and
so so I want to spend more of our time
talking about how do we alter the
metabolic and contractile properties so
another thing that makes skeletal muscle
extremely unique is the fact that it is
multinucleated so now remember the
nucleus of the cell is what what holds
your DNA it relegates all activities and
tells the cell to grow shrink die repair
or any other necessary function the
overwhelming majority of cells in all
biology are single nucleated some of
them actually get very interesting when
they have two or three but SK muscle has
thousands per cell this allows it to
actually have such extreme size because
now we have more relegation centers
throughout it I can give you an analogy
here let's imagine you're running a
business and you want to have a branch
manager at every one of your offices
well if you only have one branch manager
it's hard to have an office in say
Chicago New York Dallas and Seattle too
many little things happen in local areas
it's hard to relegate and to change
things quickly but if you could put a
manager in every single location the
success of each brand as well as the
speed and turnover goes up that's
effectively what your muscle cells are
doing they're putting a lot of nuclei in
a lot of different places so that allows
not only the size to expand but where
this really matters is the adaptability
your muscle is
hyperresponsive to things that are
happening in a short time window across
a broad domain of insults what I mean
this could be responsive to physical
contraction to blood flow nutrient
availability glucose oxygen hormones
lifestyle factors all of these things
are being measured and monitored by
skeletal muscle and because it has the
ability to adapt in multiple segments it
can do that and it can do that very
quickly giving you some firm numbers on
this nuclei let's say that biceps brachi
muscle we talked about a second ago was
10 cm long it may have something in the
neighborhood of 3,000 nuclei if you were
to then count up all the muscle fibers
in total this would mean you would have
in the ballpark of 700 50 million nuclei
in the entire biceps muscle you extend
this out to all 600 plus of your muscles
and that puts you somewhere in the
neighborhood of around 500 billion
nuclei throughout your entire body
that's how responsive an Adaptive
skeletal muscle is to everything you're
doing in your life we're going to talk a
lot more about these myonuclei in future
episodes because as I mentioned they are
the primary place that are going to
regulate how your muscle cells respond
and change to external stressors but
what regulates the contractile and
metabolic properties that's actually
something different and it's what we
call the muscle fiber type you've
probably heard of this referred to as a
fast twitch or slow twitch muscle fibers
but it actually extends beyond that now
on the surface that's a fine broad
explanation but we can go a little bit
past that and I think it's helpful to do
so without being unnecessarily
exhaustive really fibers can be
classified as the following slow twitch
or another way to say that is type one
and then your fast twitch fibers are
broken down into two major categories
your type 2A as well as your 2x fibers
many of the properties are the same
between all these fiber types the micro
Anatomy how they're designed all the
things we've talked about how they're
wrapped in connected tissue their my
nucleation status etc etc the properties
that are really distinct are again the
contractile and metabolic ones slow
twitch fibers tend to be but are not
always smaller in fact in in endurance
trained individuals they can often times
be larger than fast TCH fibers but their
contraction is exactly that the twitch
or the speed of contraction is slower
doesn't necessarily mean the strength or
force behind the contraction is smaller
or less it's just that it contracts a
little bit slower the advantage though
is they tend to be highly fatigue
resistant they are better at utilizing
fat as a fuel source they have more
mitochondria and they're overall good at
what we call anti-gravity or postural so
when you think about slow chouch fibers
they tend to be the ones that are on
kind of all day keep you upright and
erect keep you moving and keep you at a
low level of contraction but
continuously fast twitch fibers
particularly the 2A fibers are really
the opposite so they're going to be
hedged more towards fast speed of
contraction but really they're not
particularly effective at fatigue
resistance they are going to prefer
using things like phosphocreatine or
carbohydrates as a fuel source and are
not as effective at things like fat or
long-term sustained contractions the
third and final type 2x are the fastest
of the bunch while your 2A and fast
switch fibers are somewhere in the
neighborhood of five to six times more
powerful than a slower type 1 fiber a 2X
fiber is in the neighborhood of 20 times
more
powerful the downside is we don't really
have any good Evidence of normal humans
having many if any pure 2x fibers oddly
enough we see it in extreme muscle
disused situations things like spinal
cord injury or coming back from Extended
space flight or situations like that and
so there's a lot of M still behind these
2x fibers we could get into that again
in maybe more detail a little bit later
so on its surface while we really have
these three distinct unique fiber types
type one type 2 a and type 2x it is
really appropriate to discuss basically
the type one and the type 2 A's from now
on now within any individual muscle you
have on your body the proportion of fast
twitch to slow twitch in other words the
amount of fast or SL fibers in that
muscle varies widely from muscle to
muscle as well as from Human to Human
now that actually determines a lot about
the function of that muscle for example
if you take say the Solus muscle which
is one of the small muscles kind of
behind the back of your calf there that
goes into your uh the bottom of your
heel that is heavily based towards slow
twitch muscle fibers depending on the
person it' be something in the
neighborhood of 70% to all the way up to
90 plus% slow twitch fibers and that's
because the primary purpose of the Solus
is to keep you standing and moving all
day it's not meant for EXP exposive
power or sprinting or jumping or
anything like that if you were to
compare that to the other major muscle
in your calf the gastrus that's almost
the exact opposite in a lot of folks it
is you know 60 plus to 70 or 80% fast
switch fibers so the gas rock is there
for the exact opposite it is there for
the explosion for the jumping and
sprinting and not necessarily to keep
you upright all day now that's not
necessarily true of other animals in
fact this is one of the things that
makes examining research in this area
important to pay attention to whether
you're looking at a study from a rat or
a mouse a cat a bear or any other animal
is that is different in fact mice the
solius is almost exclusively if not 100%
slow twitch and other muscles like the
plantaris might be the opposite 100%
fast twitch and so why there's clearly
important information we can gather
there is not necessarily a direct and
equal comparator so as I mentioned the
amount of fast twitch and slow twitch
the fiber proportions in the muscle
groups varies within your own body it
also varies from person to person so if
I were to biopsy myself as I have
several dozen times I would know and see
that say in my vasos Calis the muscle on
the outside which is the most common
muscle to biopsy for a number of reasons
it has the least amount of nerve
inovations there's no major blood
vessels flowing through there it's easy
to access it tends to be quite large I
don't have to go past any other muscle
groups etc etc So within that muscle I
have seen people in my laboratory as
high as 90% plus slow twitch
as well as up to 85% fast witch and
everywhere in between and so the
quadricep again the VL specifically here
is meant to really be responsive to
training and we'll talk about this more
later other muscles like the Solus
spinal Erectors um other muscles say in
your fingers or eyes are not necessarily
going to change as much it would be very
difficult to convert your Solus into an
exclusive fast switch muscle fiber
because it's really meant to do one job
and the overall stimuli that you provide
to it is fairly similar right it doesn't
really matter what kind of exercise or
training intervention you put how many
Plyometrics or Sprints you do the vast
majority of time that your Solus is
Contracting it's still because you're
standing and so there's just not a lot
of change that can happen there the VL
is quite different since it is so
important in all knee extension and
really hip movement it's going to be
hyper responsive to what you're asking
it to do so again can vary heavily
within your body as well as from person
to person and we'll talk about more of
this stuff later but you as you've
already heard me allude
to your fiber type again the proportion
of fast and slow twitch is hyper
responsive to Lifestyle we know
extensively for decades now that it will
respond to both changes in exercise as
well as the removal of that so some of
the classic Dallas bed rest studies
where they put people into bed where
their head was something like 6° below
their legs so you can imagine laying on
on a bed uh with a slight backwards tilt
so your head is a little bit below your
feet are a little bit above and we've
done this for up to 50 plus days and
what we're doing there is trying to
simulate both space flight this was
initially done in preparation for
thinking humans were going to go to the
moon or further for extended time as
well as it's actually represents a nice
model of Aging you can actually simulate
upwards of a decade of Aging in about 10
days to bed rest or so and so we get a
really good grasp of what happens when
you go into disuse similar for you have
to go into a cast post surgery or
something like that so we see in those
models of of inact forced inactivity as
well as any number of exercise training
studies uh looking simply at individuals
cross-sectionally so those that have
exercised for long periods of time
throughout their life compared to those
who haven't any of these interventions
you want to look at and we see
hyperresponsiveness in your fiber type
profile based upon your physical
activity other interventions that are
less well understood but are also quite
interesting that we will discuss in
depth later things like uh
nutriceuticals uh vitamins minerals phal
chemicals have been shown to alter fiber
type in extreme concentrations now
whether or not small changes in your
diet say how much carbohydrates or
protein you're eating or any
supplementation can actually reach
concentrations high enough to alter
fiber type is yet to be determined I'm
not really aware of any research showing
that but certainly we have seen that in
in many models again where we can give
them non-physiological doses but even
stuff as well as Hyperbaric or or
extensive oxygen concentrations
alterations in CO2 intake and things
like that have also again mostly in
animal models shown to alter fiber type
so whether or not this actually happens
in a normal human circumstance is not as
relevant right now but it's just
highlighting the concept of how
responsive this muscle is to everything
you're doing in your life I'd like to
take a quick break and thank our
sponsors today's episode has brought to
you by David David makes protein bars
unlike anything I've ever encountered
they have an amazing 28 g of protein
only 150 calories and 0 gram of sugar
that's right 28 gr of protein and 75% of
its calories come from protein this is
50% higher than the next closest protein
bar honestly it's the best tasting
protein bar I've ever had in my life by
a mile now I don't usually talk about
products before their launch but These
Bars by David represent a meaningful
breakthrough in both macronutrients and
taste and when you guys try it you will
know what I mean after lots of research
and development these David protein bars
are releasing to the public in September
of
2024 the macronutrients one more time
are 28 g of protein 150 calories and 0 g
of sugar and they do this with excellent
ingredients if you're interested in
trying these bars for yourself you can
go to davidpro
docomo to purchase if possible
or be notified when they're available
again that's
david.com perform to purchase if
possible or be notified when they are
available today's episode is also
brought to you by ag1 ag1 is a
foundational nutrition greens supplement
that means ag1 provides a variety of
vitamins minerals probiotics prebiotics
and adaptogens in an easy to drink
greens powder initially I was very
skeptical of ag1 as I am with all
supplement companies frankly but after
months of discussions with their lead
nutrition scientists and the team at ag1
I've been impressed by their commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and rigorous testing to
ensure that every single batch is free
of banned substances allergens heavy
metals microbes pesticides herbicides
residual solvents and mot toxins it's
even earned the prestigious NSF
certified for sport third-party testing
approval now ag1 is not a replacement
for eating Whole Foods but it is a great
way to fill in the gaps and it's been
big help pushing some of my clients just
in the right direction for eating more
high quality foods because it helps them
with Cravings digestion and many other
benefits now not everyone needs to
consume greens powders but if you're
going to do so you better make sure it
actually includes the ingredients that
it claims to and that those ingredients
are of the best sourcing if you'd like
to try ag1 you can go to drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus K2 again that's drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus K2 so in my opinion the key take
home is that things like your fiber type
again which regulate the contract on
nature how fast and Powerful your muscle
fibers contract as well as their
metabolic properties how effective they
are at using fats and carbohydrates as a
fuel source how efficient they are at
bringing in nourishment and getting out
waste products much of this is regulated
by its fiber type and your fiber type in
general is responsive to changes in
activity now if we were to have to
compare the responsiveness of the fast
twitch fibers to the slow twitch fibers
it is very clear fast twitch fibers are
more reactive to things like physical
activity changes whether or not you can
increase or decrease the amount of Soul
fibers in response to exercise I think
that evidence is clear but it is of a
much smaller magnitude than the
plasticity within the fast switch fibers
now why that's critical then is unless
you do something about it from an
exercise perspective you're going to
lose many of your fast witch fibers as
you age a really nice example of this a
paper published in the last few weeks
looked at lifelong strength trainers now
this is interesting because while we are
just starting to get data on lifelong
exercisers almost all have that has been
in arobic or endurance-based exercisers
we're just starting to come on board
with these lifelong strength trainers
and what that paper found was that that
activity to strength training basically
over your entire life was able to
preserve fast twitch fiber
concentrations however the endurance
training was not and so it's not to say
that strength training is more important
or better for your health at all but it
is simply saying these fiber types are
lost you're not able to get them back
but you can preserve that or murate that
loss by chronic strength training now
you're going to care about these faster
fibers for a couple of reasons
while we will acknowledge that both fast
and slow fibers are critically important
for overall muscle Health what makes
fast wch fibers unique is a few things
the first is that again they express the
greatest capacity for force and power
production this is obviously critically
important for young folks trying to
enhance uh their you know Club head
speed on their driver when they're
playing golf or individuals as they move
throughout age think about scenarios in
which you need to move your foot in
front of you to catch yourself from a
fall you want to be explosive enough to
go upstairs without it fatiguing you you
need to have power to lift something up
overhead quickly before it collapses
back down in you or any number of
reasons in which you need to have
strength and power as you age now the
way that you regulate Force production
extends Beyond just what the muscle
fibers themselves can do unfortunately
I've got to give a little bit of credit
back to the neuroscientist folks here
because really this is a combination of
nervous system as well as muscle fiber
characteristics all of your muscle
fibers are combined into what are called
motor units so the definition of a motor
unit is the motor nerve as well as all
the muscle fibers within that package
now all of those fibers within that
motor unit will be of the same fiber
type so fast twitch or slow twitch and
they're not necessarily laying next to
each other in the muscle they are spread
out both Superior and inferior they're
deep within the muscle belly they're
kind of all spread out there and this
allows you to control and not have
movement so when you activate a
motor unit not only does this contract
all of the muscle fibers in that unit it
contracts them all fully that's called
the all or none principle and so when
you flip the switch and turn on that
motor unit you pass that activation
threshold it activates and contracts all
the muscle fibers in that unit to their
fullest potential what you can't do is
turn a muscle fiber itself on at 60% or
70% or 80% so the only way you relegate
force production across an entire
movement
is to actually turn on or off more or
less motor
units the example here say I would like
to take my hand and reach it up towards
my eyeball and lightly touch my eye now
I recognize and realize this is only
going to take a small amount of force to
move the weight necessary to move my
hand to lightly touch my eye if I were
to do that too hard I would smash my
finger into my eyeball and that would
hurt and so what I do is I start with
what are called Low threshold motor
units so these are motor units there
they're very susceptible to firing or or
Contracting and they activate in this
case very slow and metabolically
efficient muscle fibers the type one
muscle fibers and so what it says is I
kind of start with the least amount
possible physiology is very lazy like
this and so I'll start with the least
amount of force necessary and this
allows me to move very slowly but with a
lot amount of control and now if I
realized that actually I had a a 5 pound
weight attached to my wrist and I had to
lift my hand with more Force than I
thought I needed I would turn on more
and more motor units and if I realized
that I had that 5B weight and then I
added a 10 PB ball to my hand I need
more and more Force production I would
slowly turn on more and more motor
units as we continue up this Cascade
again the size principle is telling us
we start with the lowest threshold
smallest motor units so this is not only
tends to be slow to muscle fibers but
it's also often times but not always
motor units that have less muscle fibers
in them the amount of muscle fibers in a
motor unit can vary highly um several of
them in your eye can be as low as a
couple of dozen uh muscle fibers in the
motor unit and those in your glutes
might be several thousand muscle fibers
so even if I activated one motor unit in
my eye I would get a small amount of
Force One motor unit in my glute might
produce you know hundreds if not higher
amount of force per motor unit because I
have more muscle fiber in that in
addition the muscle fibers might be of
larger size in the glute and smaller
size in the eye because we need more
motor control there and less Force
production something like the eye again
is meant to be highly precise with its
movement very low margin of air I don't
need to get there particularly hard I
need to get there sort of quickly but I
need to be under control the glute in
this example uh this is your your your
uh butt muscle one of any of your large
butt muscles they don't necessarily need
to have a lot of fine-tune Precision
with the movement they just need to
contract with a lot of force and so the
way that these motor units is set up is
in large part determinant of how they
produce force and then again what the
function of that muscle actually is so
to go back to what we were talking about
a second ago if I'm trying to produce
this finger into my eyeball and I need
to produce more and more Force I slowly
activate more motor units if I've
realized the point where I need more
Force beyond that I will increase and
start activating the higher threshold
motor units that also now start to tend
to be faster twitch motor units and if I
need extreme amounts of force I will
activate the highest threshold which are
the highest and probably where we're
going to get into our type 2 x fibers if
we have any of them at all and so what
happens then if we're playing the story
backwards is any movement at all in a
muscle almost always includes the slow
twitch motor units but only when I start
demanding High Force production do I
activate and engage the fast switch
muscle fibers if I then go weeks months
years or decades without doing anything
of high Force those motor units just
never get activated eventually what can
happen is denervation which means the
nerve stops attaching to the muscle
fibers many of the muscle fibers die off
we talked about that earlier right the
amount of muscle fibers in a muscle
reduces with aging if you don't know
anything about it and then also we see
changes in motor units so not only is
our ability to produce Force go down but
our motor control goes down because
we've lost the amount of motor units
going into a muscle sometimes we can see
what happens called muscle fiber type
grouping and so we'll see a nerve
denervation an axon uh that that is gone
if you will the muscle fibers are still
viable and so a neighboring motor unit
will actually obtain them and if they
were say a fast twitch muscle fiber but
now they're in a slow twitch mod unit
they will convert that fiber type over
to slow and so you see these big patches
or groupings of slow fibers as opposed
to them being spread out throughout the
muscle which reduces our motor control
and smoothness of muscle contraction so
going back to our original Point here
it's incredibly important that we do
something to preserve our fast twitch
fibers because if we don't we're going
to lose them and that then becomes
extraordinarily difficult to bring them
back especially once we've lost the
fiber number returning muscle function
say your strength is actually very
manageable through aging but increasing
the amount of muscle fibers as we age is
very difficult so once we lose them
they're basically gone for life before
we go any further let's quickly go back
and recap what we've talked about the
importance of skeleton muscle extends
far beyond sport performance or
Aesthetics in fact it's important for a
number of physiological factors across
basically every organ system in your
body we also know that skeletal muscle
is uniquely responsive to changes in the
external environment it is hyper
adaptable to things like changes in
physical activity nutrition or various
other lifestyle factors in fact what I
would call the superpower of skeletal
muscle is its ability to respond and
adapt both quickly as well as
permanently we talked about how the
muscles fibers themselves are
multinucleated which allows them that
extended adaptability as well as come in
various forms fast twitch and slow
twitch fibers the fast twitch fibers
being more difficult to preserve and
probably require some sort of steady and
consistent exposure to high Force
demands over the course of your life in
order to maintain so what I'd like to do
now is walk through the three eyes
investigate interpret and intervene for
both muscle quality and muscle quantity
and I want to do them separately and
that's because while there's a giant
overlap between the two they are
independent factors let me give you an
example while there's a clear
relationship between muscle size and
muscle strength such that generally
bigger muscles are are generally
stronger that's not necessarily always
the case we can see number of examples
here take any sport that is a weight
class based sport Wrestling Boxing
weightlifting powerlifting generally the
best of the best will increase their
performance in this case say strength as
muscle size goes up so clearly there is
a relationship between if you have more
muscle mass you potentially have the
ability to create more Force but that
said if you walked out to the general
population or even in athletes just
because you find an athlete who has more
muscle that doesn't necessarily mean
they're going to be stronger so again
there's a clear relationship here but it
is not necessarily one to one in
addition it's incredibly clear and
simple to increase strength or power
without necessarily changing muscle size
at all these are all protocols we will
go over and discuss at the end of this
of our episode today but there's a
relationship here in fact I think a
really nice way to highlight this even
further is a recent publication of mine
now this was led by a colleague of M
Tommy wood a neuroscientist at the
University of Washington and what we did
is we went into the National Database
this is what's referred to as n hannes
so this is a giant National Database of
kind of a study that they run every
single year they collect a bunch of data
from participants they put them into
these big opsource pools and they may do
IQ testing um strength testing blood
work etc etc and scientists can come in
and use these for any purpose now
they've been running an Hanes for
several decades and so you have many
many many years of analysis that you can
go back into and and poke around in well
Tommy and myself and the rest of our
team did that and in our paper we found
a couple of interesting things here
within the population of participants
that we analyze there was no
relationship whatsoever between their
physical strength and their muscle
mass in fact there was also no
relationship at all between their amount
of muscle mass they had and their
physical activity background what this
tells us is in this population alone
they acred their muscle mass from
non-exercise Pathways what we did
actually find was a strong relationship
between muscle strength and cognitive
function but that's something we'll talk
about in a further episode so my point
here is when you look at the
relationship between again muscle mass
and strength they can
overlap they can also not um we can see
further evidence of this when we look at
things like mitochondrial Health
testosterone concentrations range of
motion a lot of these things are
somewhat linked to muscle size but not
necessarily in the last example think
about this as if you were to take
somebody who has more muscle mass that
will tell you actually very little about
their range of motion or
flexibility if that extends to a certain
point of course excessive amounts of
muscle mass may start contributing and
so again there's an overlap there but
there's so much distinction between the
two I think it's important that we
actually treat them as almost separate
variables we're going to start off with
muscle quantity or muscle size the gold
standard here in research would be to
use something like an MRI or an
ultrasound to get a high resolution
cross-sectional image of an individual
muscle or muscle groups think again the
quadriceps hamstring muscles elbow
flexors etc etc the benefit of this of
course is high vitility accuracy and
precision the downside is it's really
only telling you about that individual
muscle or muscle group it's really only
covering that portion of it so where the
MRI is shot it may necessarily cover say
the part of the quadricep that's close
to your hip or close to your knee if the
MRI was taken at say the midpoint of it
doesn't really allow you to access or
compare the right leg to the left leg
unless you also image that leg and then
really for this conversation the most
challenging part about that is uh it is
extremely unrealistic for most people to
do this would cost you a ton of money
and be very challenging to get access to
so it's not a real viable solution for
most people that said new technologies
are coming online there are companies
like Springbok which allow you to do
exactly what I just talked about so this
is a full body MRI and this is quite
different than using something to say
scan for early cancer diagnosis or
something like that this is really for
the assessment of muscle quality
quantity rather and so you can go in an
MRI takes about an hour or so and they
will be able to capture an image each
individual muscle you have in your body
and give you a visual in three-dimension
feed feedback of the muscle volume of
them which again allows you to compare
say all the muscles in your rotator cuff
to each other compare the one on the
right side the left side front side to
Backside etc etc these are available
throughout at least America right now in
a number of MRI facilities it is quite
expensive still for the average consumer
and it's not uh usable and available
again worldwide so if you want those to
go after a gold standard that would
probably be your best bet if that's not
available or you're more interested in
something that can be used anywhere you
have a couple of other options and those
would be things like your appendicular
muscle mass measurement or your fat-free
mess now both of those metrics can be
used to create what's called an index in
a second here I'm going to tell you what
some of those standard numbers are and
those are widely available based on your
age or sex to be able to get an idea of
where you should be at uh on those
scales but quickly when I say alular
what I'm talking about is basically how
much muscle do you have in the
appendicies so your arms and legs that
differs from your fatf free mass index
and it's important for me to point out
that's not necessarily representative of
your total amount of skeletal muscle
that actually can be measured in other
ways and would be a separate idea so
what I mean by that is when you think
about your body if you want to globally
say okay we're going to bucket
everything into the amount of fat I have
and the amount of non-fat I have that's
not necessarily only muscle it includes
things like water muscle glycogen bone
minerals and things like that and so
it's actually a pretty decent estimate
of how much muscle you have but not
nearly as precise and specific as again
some sort of MRI imaging could give you
now in order to appropriately calculate
these values the best way is if you can
get yourself into a a dexa scan or
something like that those are
traditionally a100 to $200 or so
available in America and plenty of other
countries worldwide so a little bit less
challenging and certainly more cost
friendly than the the previous MRI stuff
but not free either and so still may be
outside of your cost range if you want
to take a step below that most home
scales come with the ability to use
what's called Bia and so this is
effectively going to tell you your body
fat percentage you can use that in
combination with your height and get a
rough estimate of your fat free mass
index again once you go down in scale
scientific accuracy you start to lose
some Fidelity of measurement but for a
lot of people that exchange of cost
difficulty accessibility might be worth
it especially if you're just looking to
see if you're close if you're trying to
see whether or not you broke a world
record we probably need to go a little
more accurate method but for those of
you that are just trying to get a basic
understanding of am I significantly
underused am I okay where am I roughly
at those are absolutely fine metrics to
take and to examine fat-free mass index
or ffmi is probably the most established
metric to look at here so I'm going to
focus mostly on that one interesting
enough enough there is no fundamental
way to calculate this there's a lot of
nuance that can go into this that can
alter your numbers in a decent amount of
way so it's important not to confuse you
even more but I do need to add that that
is not as simple maybe as one would
would hope uh your hydration status on
the day and other factors like that can
alter it enough so again if you're
looking for high
Precision maybe pay attention to that
but if you're just trying to get an
estimate this is still going to give you
phenomenal numbers there's also hundreds
of papers published on this and so you
have a great scientific background to
give you that context of where you're at
as an incredibly rough number when we're
looking at that ffmi so that fat free
mass index score for men I generally
want to see them coming in at over 20
and for women something like 16.5 again
this will scale Up and Down based on age
and you can look at a chart to see
exactly where you're at I'll give you
some examples here in a second but
that's kind of the collective number I
want to look at now to give you a little
bit of context of what some of the gold
standards are here of total amount of
muscle mask we can have a little more
fun I want to take you all the way back
to 1995 there's this classic study that
came out and it basically said all right
the average Jim goer is something like
the neighborhood of 21.5 to 22 on an
ffmi score and they actually theorized
at that point that the only way to get
past a score of 25 was to be to use
exogenous hormones and against
specifically testosterone now another
reminder here I'm not encouraging or
promoting the use of hormones especially
outside of working directly with your
doctor but this is what they're
establishing what they're trying to
identify is what is the genetic
limitation of muscle in other words how
much muscle can a normal human have
outside of using exogenous hormones and
the answer they came up with was 24.8 or
was sort of roughly 25 that's been
disputed since then but that gave us a
ballpark and understanding so when
you're looking at your scores if you
realize that you're you know certainly
you know in the 2425 area this puts you
close to what normal people are going to
be outside of again exogenous hormone
use but there's a lot of examples where
people blow way past this of course we
never necessarily know if somebody had
used things like testostrone in the past
but I'm going to make a pretty good
argument for you right now that it's
absolutely possible to go past that in
fact if you look at someone like Arnold
Schwarzenegger in his Heyday kind of at
his peak of performance his FFM my score
was about 28 now we obviously know
Arnold has his history and past with
exogenous hormone use and so that still
doesn't really change the case of saying
well can we get past this 25
marker naturally well let's look at some
of the evidence here to give you a
little bit of of scoring context here if
you're at 23 and a half remember 25 is
the established limit what we think to
be natural Arnold was at 28 with
extensive steroid use if you're at 23 A2
for most men this is going to put you in
the 99th percentile so already puts you
in a phenomenal position however there
are data initially the first set of
studies came out in sumo wrestlers and
now these are individuals that were well
over 400 lbs giving them something in
the neighborhood of 260 to 270 pounds of
lean body mass now again that doesn't
mean muscle mass lean body mass is
including bone and water and things like
that but still you know 260 or so pounds
of lean body mass is a t
to move around in your system this gave
them an FFM my score of about
35 now there's actually a famous case
report that came out of one of the best
powerlifters of all time Ray Williams
now of course his name wasn't used in
the paper but effectively everyone knows
who that was and he scored a
41 on that metric which just tells you
how enormous uh and an incredible
athlete that Ray is again don't know
about his story use in the past doesn't
matter what I'm trying to show you right
now is just what is the human potential
for total amount of muscle mass we can
put on a
frame now the magical number that tends
to be thrown around here in terms of
amount of lean body mass one can have is
somewhere in the neighborhood of 110 to
120 kilos translation 230 PBS or so
something like that the example I gave
you earlier of course is a little bit
higher than that but that tends to be
the kind of spot we can be as you start
manipulating body weight hydration
status what that does to muscle glycogen
pulling water the system again this can
alter this number sort of dayto day so
it's a little bit hard to interpret but
that's the kind of number we're going to
put um in terms of what they was this
would put you in in terms of absolute
muscle
mass probably 60 kilos or so um and the
reason is maybe we'll back up one quick
second lean body mass of let's just say
12 kilos is kind of the upper limit of
what we think you have well about 50 40
somewhere between 45 to 50% of that will
actually be skeletal muscle and so if
you have
122 kilos of lean body mass and half of
that is muscle this would give you the
stratosphere of about 60 kilos or so of
total amount of muscle mass that's about
the um upper limit of what you'll ever
see a human can have obviously the
numbers I'm giving you here are all in
men for women that number gets
significantly lower but that just kind
of gives you a ballpark of how much
skeletal muscle one could have how much
lean muscle they would have and then
what their corresponding FF and my score
would be there's two other things I want
to point out before we move on and the
first is dealing with asymmetry now
we're going to talk a lot about
functional asymmetry so when one muscle
is stronger than another and vice versa
but the actual amount of muscle Size
Matters as well we don't have as much
concrete data on this and it also
depends on your activities so for
example if you are an athlete of any
kind it may behoove you to have some
amount of asymmetry this allows you to
create things like rotation and torque
to be able to throw a baseball 100 miles
hour or to hit a golf ball 400 yards or
whatever the case may be but that said
there's clearly a point in which a
symmetry within a muscle from side to
side front to back Etc is
detrimental functionality is different
in terms of quantity right now some
folks are going to say 5% others might
cut that line at about 10% so if you
were to get an analysis and look at say
how much muscle you had uh from a dexa
scan you're able to identify maybe your
right leg versus your left leg or
something like that you would want to
keep an eye on about that 10% anything
more than that is probably going to be a
flag that there's some sort of issue or
potential issue in the future so total
amount of muscle mass ffmi is a great
way to go about it asymmetry pay
attention to more than about 10% and the
second thing I wanted to point out
here is what does it look like when I
gain too much muscle and I want to be
clear here and I believe that we've
showed that in the recent paper we've
published and that is
excessive amounts of skeletal mass is
not detrimental in any way so there does
not seem to be an upper limit where it
actually starts compromising your
physical health now of course if you've
gained muscle from non exercise venues
like what we saw in our enhan database
in our recent paper then that's not
great so an example here would be if
you've just gained a bunch of body fat
and because of that some muscle came
along for the ride that would be what we
consider to be muscle that I got acred
from non-exercise Habits this is is not
going to be advantageous to your health
but if it is acur from exercise there
doesn't seem to be any evidence at all
that suggests this is negative there are
some papers out there that I think have
made mistakes in identifying that after
a certain point an increase in muscle
mass is actually negative and again
having analyzed some of those things
myself and our recent paper I think we
found clear evidence that that is not
the case there are other practical
considerations if you've exercised
excessively you've done it poorly or
other things that had led to injury of
course all those things were true what
I'm trying to argue is the simple fact
of having additional muscle mass itself
is not detrimental to Health in any way
can be associated with other things that
are bad for you that lead to injury and
other metabolic problems but the
excessive amount of muscle mass on its
surface is only going to Aid in both
your health and performance we're going
to make a number of these charts
available to you in the show Nots but
again please acknowledge that they do
vary a little bit from to study so
depending on which population was in a
particular paper or how it was analyzed
the values might be a little bit
different but you're going to get you
pretty close nonetheless I want to give
you a couple of numbers just to get you
started though now these work on
percentiles what this means is when I
say one percentile that means the lowest
amount of muscle mass 99 percentile is
the highest obviously as we've been
describing you don't want to be low in
muscle whether you're an athlete or
someone just interested in overall
wellness and Health and Longevity higher
is better I actually personally prefer
people to be in the 95th percentile or
more but I'm going to walk you through
what this kind of looks like across the
25th 50th 70th and then potentially up
to 95th percentile for men to be in the
25th percentile year FFM my score would
be about 17.9 and women that would be
15.1 now notice how as you go from the
25th to 50th percentile again
representing right in the statistical
average or right in the middle you've
gone from for men 17.9
up to 19.1 or so and for women you've
gone from
15.1 up to 15.9 or almost 16 and so
these numbers are not going to be huge
in terms of what it looks like on paper
but that it does represent a large
change in the total amount of muscle
mass you have if you were to go from
that 50th percentile to 75th you've now
gone up to
20.4 for men and
16.8 for women as I said I actually
prefer people to be in the 95th per
higher because it provides no
disadvantage whatsoever in overall
health and performance that's going to
look like something like north of 22 for
men and north of
18.1 for
women of course if you're extremely
ambiguous and you want to challenge Ray
Williams and his record of 41 by all
means be my guest and please report back
to me if you've accomplished such a feat
ffmi is not an intuitive number or score
so if I were to give you an ffmi score
that puts you in the 75th percentile you
wouldn't really know what that means so
let me explain you how that number is
calculated and run you through a couple
of samples and I'll do it both in the
empirical as well as in the metric units
now we know science Works in kilos so we
will start there globally when we think
about body composition we're thinking
about how much muscle do I have versus
how much fat but as I said it's actually
a little more complicated than that so
if you were to get something like a dexa
scan done or even stepped on a scale and
that gave you your body fat percentage
what it's telling you is what percentage
of your overall body weight is fat
versus what is lean body mass and
remember that lean mass is not just
skeletal muscle it is skeletal muscle
plus bone and water and things like that
so as a sample calculation let's try
this let's say you were 5 fo 10 and
weighed 100 kilos now I'm picking 100
kilos because it makes the math very
easy and for many of you listening
you're going to appreciate the fact that
made the math somewhat simple for you so
if I were to be 100 kilos in weight and
my body fat percentage was 25 that means
25 of those kilos are fat and 75 are
nonfat as I said earlier most people
that are decently trained anyways of
their lean body mass somewhere between
45 to 50% of that is actual skeletal
muscle and so if we were to take that
75 divide that by two assuming 50% this
would mean you probably have something
like 37.5 kilg of actual muscle in your
body and again 25 kilos of fat if you
wanted to calculate your ffmi score from
that all you would have to do is go back
to that lean body mass number so in
kilograms so in this case 75 and divide
that by your height so how tall you are
in met squared so if you're 5' 10 in
tall this is 70 in which would be about
1.7 78 M so you take
1778 square that and then you take 75
and divide it by that number this would
produce in this particular case an ffmi
score of
23.7 pretty decent overall you can also
in it if you looked at somebody who's 5'
10 they're two or 100 kilos and 25% body
fat this is an individual with a lot of
muscle mass and so this probably makes
sense that they'd be on the upper end of
that Spectrum I'm run through that exact
same thing now um in pounds for those of
you that prefer that method so 100 kilos
would be 220 lb so just take the kilos
and multiply it by
2.2 if you were to run the exact same
equation so again assuming 25% body fat
this would leave you with 165 pounds of
lean body mass and 55 lbs of fat Mass
take that 165 again L assume 50% so
we'll divide that by two and you would
have 822 lbs of lean mass but
nonetheless we'll go back up and you'll
take that6 65b number you would need
then to convert that to kilograms which
means you divide it by 2.2 which would
put you right back into that uh 75
kilogram number take that divide that by
the same units uh in meters squared of
your height and that would give you that
same exact FF on my score so very easy
to convert your body weight in pounds to
kilos convert your height in inches to
centimeters and then convert that to
meters go online Google conversion it'll
do that in two seconds for you and
you're able to quickly calculate your
ffmi our third eye of intervene which is
a fancy way of saying what interventions
do I do what stimuli do I introduce to
Aid in muscle growth now I'm not really
going to discuss muscle loss I don't
really see any advantage to doing that
so we'll focus on simply augmenting or
increasing muscle mass couple things to
get you started while nutrition is an
important consideration here I need to
make sure that it's completely clear
here resistance sectr size is by far
the greater stimuli of muscle growth
relative to nutrition really from this
perspective we need to make sure we have
sufficient calories which is to be said
as hypercaloric so we need a little bit
more calories than we're burning to just
stay alive and mostly we need to focus
on protein here 1.6 gr per kilogram of
body weight is a great place to start
now I personally prefer a little bit
higher 2.2 G per kilogram which is about
1 gr per pound but actually I believe
the science is is pretty clear here
suggesting that going from one .6 to 2.2
is not really going to increase the
amount of muscle you're you're growing
and if it is it's not going to be by
much and so if you prefer to be at 1.6
that's fine higher is absolutely okay as
well and it may Aid in some people in
some circumstances but going below 1.6
seems to reduce the amount of muscle you
can grow so we want to be at least that
number from a training perspective you
want to start by focusing on your big
muscle groups now if you have a
particular muscle or group of muscles
that you want to increase for any number
of reasons say you've identified an
asymmetry have a personal preference you
enjoy that more you just want to have a
muscle group grow larger for some
aesthetic reasons that's absolutely fine
focus on those but you really shouldn't
omit everything else either it's
critically important to maintain posture
and Joint Integrity by ensuring we have
adequate muscle surrounding each joint
which basically means we need to address
each muscle at some point throughout the
week we can certainly emphasize some
more than others that's no problem
whatsoever but we don't want to leave
big chunks of muscles completely
unchallenged that's going to present
problems more likely if not now down the
road so we also want to challenge these
muscles across multiple stimuli meaning
exercises so whether you prefer your
body weight machines dumbbells kettle
bells or any number of other strategies
those are absolutely fine all are
incredibly effective and at the highest
level it actually doesn't really matter
that much which of those strategies you
try because at the end of the day it's
just about stimulating the muscle
however you go about that is absolutely
fine so you have lots of options there
perhaps in a future episode we'll get
into the the details and spend the
entire discussion on that going over
pros and cons of those different
strategies and tactics but for now at at
again the most zoomed out level you've
got a tremendous amount of options
regarding which exercise uh you select
and which modes and methodologies you do
to engage that resistance exercise
the range of motion is critical you want
to use the largest range of motion you
can while still being safe and
protective of both the exercising joint
as well as the joint above it and below
it so an example here let's just say
you're interested in growing your
quadriceps you want to have a lot of
activity over both the knee and hip
joint but you want to make sure that
you're doing though that in a case in
which you're not compromising your low
back and say your feet and so making
sure we're protecting the joints above
and below the muscle group is important
as
well so we really want to challenge our
muscles as much as we can in a variety
of ways there in terms of how much to do
the repetitions per set doesn't really
matter such that you can have success in
a number of them anywhere between say as
low as five repetitions per set all the
way up to 30 or more repetitions per set
can be equally effective for muscle
growth the total amount of sets per week
is probably the bigger determinant from
there you probably want to be in the
neighborhood of about 15 to 20 working
sets per muscle per week if you were to
break that down let's say you were
focusing again on your hamstrings
muscles if you did three sets on day one
three sets on day two and three sets on
day three that would give you a total of
nine working sets per week that's
probably a little bit too low but if you
did two hamstring exercises each day
three sets each that'd be six sets day
one six sets day two six sets day three
and now you're up to close to 18 working
sets per month per week rather that's a
pretty good spot to be in lots of things
we could talk about there in terms of
advanc athletes and Elite but
structurally and roughly that's going to
put you in the ballpark that's going to
be enough stimulus for most people to
grow most of the time last consideration
here is frequency as I sort of alluded
to here somewhere between two to three
days per week per muscle group is a
great way to go about it MO is fine as
well if you can handle the recovery less
than two days a week is also
theoretically possible there's excellent
research showing one day a week per
muscle group is sufficient to mus to
grow muscle it does become practically
challenging though because now you got
to fit all those working sets into a
single day and that is challenging both
in the length of the workout as well as
how sore and how much damage you create
so what I recommend here is what I call
the 72-h hour rule which is every 72
hours or so work each of your muscles to
a nice pumper contraction remember we
want to stimulate muscle growth here but
we we don't want to annihilate the
muscle either excessive fatigue and
damage and soreness does not Aid in
muscle growth and can actually harm our
ability to come back and train again in
the next session or even the one
following that which would then reduce
our overall total volume so enough
intensity enough difficulty to stimulate
growth but not so much that we
completely annihilate it we got we got
to be able to repeat that every 72 hours
or so so again the way I say it take it
to a nice pump a nice contraction
whatever that means to you and that's
going to get a lot of people in a close
enough ballpark to Growing muscle I'd
like to take a quick break and thank our
sponsors today's episode is brought to
you by Maui Nei venison Maui Nei venison
is my absolute favorite thing to eat
period it's beyond delicious and the
highest protein per calorie meat you
will find Maui venison is 100% wild
harvested meat not fenced farmed or fed
in any way the venison is ethically and
sustainably hunted on the island of Maui
and is far beyond the quality of any
beef grass-fed or whatever you've ever
tried in your life and I know cuz I grew
up in the country and I've tried it all
it's easy to cook and tastes incredible
my wife and small kids absolutely inhale
it and the jerky s are a daily staple
for me with 10 gram of protein and just
55 calories I literally ate two just now
and I sent it to school with my kids all
the time while Maui Nei venison offers
the highest quality meat available there
is a catch supplies are limited by
Nature responsible population management
means they won't go beyond the Harvest
capacity memberships are the best way to
ensure that you can get the meat you
want whenever you want it so be sure to
secure your spot now Mau Nei venison is
offering perform listeners 20% off their
first purchase of jerky sticks fresh
Venison and bone broth while supplies
last the bone broth by the way has 25
gram of protein in it itself visit Maui
venisoncooking in the industry guides
users through effective and easy to
follow lifting programs all through
their hypertrophy app these programs are
designed by the absolute best in the
industry including one of my absolute
favorite sports scientists and
professional bodybuilder Dr Mike Israel
you may recognize that name because I've
referenced him and his work countless
times over the years so whether you're
looking to put on muscle gain strength
or both these programs will help you
achieve your goals and have produced
results in literally thousands of men
and women Renaissance periodization also
has a diet app that is backed by the
latest science and innovation in the
fields of nutrition and takes the
complexity out of dieting helping you
achieve your ideal body composition if
you'd like to try Renaissance
periodization go to RP strength.com
perform to save up to $50 off of your
subscription again that's rpst
strength.com perform to save up to $50
off your subscription so now that you
have a better understanding of how to
identify inter interpret and then modify
the amount of muscle you have let's now
talk about the quality of muscle this is
not as straightforward I can't give you
a simple equation or run you through a
quick math problem because quality means
different things to different people in
different scenarios so rather than try
to give you an exhaustive list of all of
them I'll start with just a couple of
examples and let you infer on past that
the first thing to consider here is
really not specific contractile
properties of an individual muscle but
collectively how you move now I'm not
going to get into this fully but really
quickly it's important to understand how
an individual moves the quality of that
which muscles are using for which muscle
group their technique how that is
portrayed across the joint is important
for all of us again whether we're in a
sporting context or just general life
and so when I'm thinking about yeah how
much muscle do I have and then also
what's the quality of that muscle I need
to be thinking about how that muscle is
actually used as a simple explanation
here I look for four basic things when
determining successfulness of human
movement if you're in a specific
sporting context you're of course going
to add your own unique flavor so how a
major league baseball pitcher moves is
going to be quite different than even
somebody like a golfer who are both in
rotational asymmetrical Sports how they
move you can expand that even beyond
that to somebody like an NBA player or a
pickle baller all of these coaches and
athletes in the individual sports are
going to want to have different muscles
move in different fashions in different
sequences I can't get into all those
details now so just stepping back and
thinking globally what are the core
principles that are true in all those
examples to me it's really four basic
elements the very first one is range of
motion are you able to go through a
range of motion in all of your joints
that is appropriate for those joints as
an example your elbow is meant to flex
and extend it can rotate internally and
externally this so imagine taking your
palm of your hand and sticking it up in
the air and then taking the palm of your
hand and sticking it towards the ground
internal and external rotation however
your elbow is not meant to bend left and
right if you want to move your hand in
closer to your body or away from your
body you actually have movement of your
shoulder joint and so an elbow has a few
ranges of motion a shoulder though can
go up and down in front and back it can
rotate and and kind of roll itself in
and so each joint has a different range
of motion it can go through so can you
go through all those range of motions in
a way that's appropriate without being
too much range of motion the second
thing we want to pay attention to here
is rough symmetry like we've talked
about a couple of times already so
symmetry means again am I okay moving
front and back within one joint or
groups of muscles and then how does that
compare to the contralateral or opposite
side so if I can lift my say right
shoulder straight out out in front of me
and I can lift it all the way over my
head so that it's pointing directly in
the sky but my left shoulder can only go
80% of the way then I have some sort of
a symmetry is it the front and back so
my shoulder on the front side of it is
twice the size of the back side of it
things like that so we want to look at
do I have Global asymmetry especially
when we're doing what is called
bilateral movements so imagine doing
like a squat picture a basic air squat
or a goblet squat where you're holding
an Implement in front of you or you're
squatting down like you would do to to
hold a child or a baby or something like
that in doing that I would want to be
looking at all of my joints and I would
do this one by one so starting at the
ankle joint I would say okay great can
my ankles go through a full range of
motion or are they restricted and then
therefore causing a movement
compensation at the knee or hip or some
other joint are they symmetrical is one
facing a different direction than the
other one does one have more range of
motion than the other one etc etc so
that's just one example of we would look
at the range of motion and symmetry
within one joint the third thing we want
to look at is stability let's imagine
that same squatting movement so I want
to look at now say my knee I'm going to
ask the same thing can my knee go
through a full range of motion is it
symmetrical so is the left knee doing
the same thing that the right knee is
doing and then thirdly now is it stable
so is the joint able to go up and down
under control without excessive wobbling
or shaking or any other movement pattern
that I'm not intending to do to me
that's stability really you're talking
now a combination of motor control and
strength but we can globally think of
that as is the joint stable when I'm
asking it to be stable human movement is
really two things it is asking a joint
or muscle or muscle groups to move in a
way that we want and also at the same
time not move in ways that we don't want
both of those are critical to moving
well the third and final element here is
simple awareness so is the individual
aware of what they're Jo is doing a lot
of times movement dysfunction like this
is simply somebody not knowing their
foot is not supposed to point in that
direction somebody not realizing that
one side is aimed in another Direction
than the other side so simply people
letting people know that their joint is
not supposed to be doing that that's not
a proper pattern it is a critical
component so from the onset and again we
can maybe have further discussions about
this in future episodes moving well
needs to have those four components at
each joint throughout our body if we can
do that we can set aside the injury risk
and stuff and and again talk about that
later and we can move on to really
performance now when I'm asking about a
muscle or muscle groups to perform I
cared about three things can it be fast
can it be strong and can it have what's
called muscular
endurance this can be expressed over a
concentric muscle action an Ecentric or
an isometric so generally when we say
concentric we're thinking about
shortening of the muscle length so
imagine doing a a bicep scirt when
you're actually taking the the dumbbell
and moving it closer towards your
shoulder or your face that muscle or
muscle group is shortening that' be the
concentric portion if you got all the
way to the top or say halfway up or any
range part of the range of motion and
you stopped the movement and held it
there that'd be isometric and then if
you lengthened it back down all the way
to the bottom that would be the Ecentric
portion of
and so I want you to have the ability to
be fast in any of those ranges of motion
or any of those muscle actions I want it
to be able to be strong in any of those
muscle actions and then I want it to
have the ability to repeat that multiple
times uh this could mean repeating
holding the position so if I could go to
say halfway up I could flex and hold it
there I want to be able to hold it for
as long as I need based on the specific
muscle or the movement I'm trying to do
or be able to perform multiple
repetitions
if we're looking at basically any style
of human movement it's going to need to
be fast it's going to have to be strong
and it has to display some semblance of
muscular nerves so if I summarize all of
this the way to investigate whether or
not you have sufficient muscle quality
has two unique Parts part one is
understanding do you move well now that
definition of move well really changes
depending on the sport or the context
the way that your hamstrings need to
contract for a 100 meter Sprinter are
quite different than somebody who wants
to just be able to hike all day or a
cross country skier or anything else so
that is context specific but I gave you
an example of four things that are
generally pretty Universal regardless
your muscles need to go through an
appropriate range of motion they need to
be symmetrical they need to be stable
and you need to be aware of what they're
doing if you're aware of the context say
you have a specific sporting outcome
then you can lean on a coach or an
individual in that area if not there are
plenty of glob mobile movement screening
tools so these are different tests you
can do that allow you to understand a
basic human movement pattern many of
them to choose from we could probably
put some in the Show links for you there
are some nuances within plenty of them
but something like that should be chosen
you have a lot of options I would
strongly recommend though picking at
least one thing from the how do I move
column in order to investigate is your
muscle functioning appropriately the
second thing then is some sort of
performance metric so this could be
something simple like a leg press
machine or more complex like a single
leg squat or anywhere in between and
within that you want to identify whether
or not the muscle is capable of moving
fast moving strong and can repeat that
performance over multiple repetitions
helping you interpret your score on a
movement screen is really challenging
without having a lot more individual
context so what I'd like to do is give
you some more straightforward and
specific examples from the metrics of
speed power and strength in sticking
with the theme of this show I wanted to
give you some context as to what the
best in the history of the world look
like for muscle speed power and strength
in my opinion no one typifies muscle
speed more so than 100 meter sprinters
this is the quintessential best test in
the world of maximum velocity and so
when we look at the best two names jump
off the chart of course from the female
perspective this is flojo the American
Sprinter and then from the male
perspective no one comes close to us
saying bu so how fast were these two
individuals well a little bit of context
here it took about 40 years and 11
individual men to drop the world record
in the 100 meter dash by about 210 of a
second from 9.95 to
9.74 bolt did nearly the same thing all
by himself he dropped the world record
by .16 seconds all the way down to 9.58
seconds seconds over the course of his
career so he himself represented almost
the same progress as the entire field
made in 40 years that's how much faster
he was than anybody else ever before him
and still to this day no one's come even
close to matching that feat in fact only
two people ever have Run 100 meter dash
in under 9.7 seconds which means us say
bolt is over a tenth of a second faster
than anyone ever in the history of the
competition now there's actually a lot
of interesting people who try to
understand and examine why he's so much
faster than anyone else there was an
interesting paper that was entirely
speculative was not from his team but
some
biomechanics uh researchers tried to
figure out what would be possible for
him to do that and the best that they
could estimate was that his fast twitch
fibers which we talked about earlier in
the show are about 177% faster than
other worldclass caliber
sprinters again this is entirely
speculation we don't know if that's true
there's no data or evidence biopsies
that's public record of Usain Bolt
although I've been on record for many
many times saying I would love to take
that biopsy if you're listening Usain
but of course some of the magic that
goes into sports performance is we don't
always get to know why people are how
they are now something else I find
extremely interesting about this is what
happens to maximum speed as we age and
the reason I'm drawing this out is we
talked earlier about how preserving
these fast switch muscle fibers is
critically important and if you look
across world records as we age in speed
activities versus strength versus
endurance a
clear pattern
emerges people drop maximum speed
capability way faster as they age then
they drew strength and then certainly
endurance in fact the world records in
most endurance-based activities really
don't change from folks who are 35 years
old to 40 or so and when they start
dropping at 45 to 50 plus it is fairly
small until we get to Advanced stage
speed on the other hand falls off a
cliff almost immediately as an example I
told you using Bolt's record just a
second ago 9.58 seconds if you go to the
first age category which is 35 years old
the world record jumps up to 9.87
seconds and that's just at 35 years old
if you're an endurance sport that
actually might be in your actual Prime
still it gets even further faster as we
go to 40 years old that record jumps to
9.93 and then at 45 it is a whopping
10.7 seconds so you're talking about now
addition of well over a second by just
going to the age of
45 to this date I'm not aware of any
human ever running a 100 meter dash in
under 10 seconds over the age of 40
years old so extraordinarily challenging
as we go on just to Rattle off a few
additional numbers uh every five years
or so you add on to age you're going to
look at additional half a second or so
increase in your 40 yard dash time for
those of you that are curious the world
record for a 100-year-old male is 26.99
seconds in fact the highest number I've
seen was just a few years ago a
105-year-old ran a 34.5 second 100 meter
dash so I'm not sure where you're at
you're welcome to go out and time
yourself on this please don't tear your
hamstring maybe warm up and try it a few
times before you go full maximum speed
but I hope most of you can come in under
that 34.5 seconds if not rest assured
there's 105-year-old out there somewhere
who will beat you in 100 meter sprint
and that's embarrassing coming back to
the female side Florence Griffith Joiner
or flojo as I referred to her earlier
still holds the world record at a time
of 10.49 seconds and to give you a
little bit of context of how dominant
that was it is still the record some
decades later and I believe there's only
one other female to ever run below a
10.6 so tremendous speed on her part we
could play the same game here as age
goes on although it is a little bit less
dramatic than the men the world record
for 35-year-old is held by a still
current in competing star Shelly and
Frasier price at 10.62 seconds as you go
up to the 40-year-old you're talking
about now again a similar half a second
or so jump uh to
11.09 seconds and then it continues
really on from there all the way to the
end there you've got a 100-year-old
coming in at a smoking
critically important and it is different
than power many of you could probably
get away with just a simple test of
power and you have a lot of options that
are more realistic and probably a little
safer for many of you if you're an
athlete or competitor of some type a lot
of ways you can go about this of course
you can use things like a force plate
which is an incredibly expensive and
fancy scale that can tell you exactly
how much force and how much time it
takes you to push the ground other
options are just simply doing something
like a vertical jump test or a broad
jump test a very very very easy rule of
thumb that I like for the broad jump and
this is again a horizontal jump so how
far out in front of yourself can you
jump is can you jump your height so if
you're 6 feet tall can you jump 6 feet
high level athletes are going to be
looking more like 9 to 10 or even 11
feet and that jump but a basic metric
for the average person is can you jump
your height vertical jump is actually my
favorite way you can do this easily with
just a tape measure you know put a put a
mark on the wall tape how high you can
jump measure that way as far as I know
and actually I checked around with a
bunch of colleagues on this there's no
scientifically verified world record for
this Guinness has their own records the
scientific Publications a little bit
different and so I actually called a
friend of mine Paul faitz Paul is a
world renowned basketball trainer has
coached and worked with some of the best
basketball players in the world and I
asked him and he told me basically in
his opinion 48 inches or so is the
highest he's ever seen and this would be
a standing vertical jump if you were to
get an approach say maybe two or three
steps to run in you might be able to
jump into the low 50s but he doesn't
really think anybody has eclipsed the 50
inch Mark in terms of a standing
vertical jump there's not extensive
evidence on vertical jump height by age
and so that's a little bit more
challenging to give you so what I would
say is again focus on something more
like that broad jump test another option
is to use machines like a proteus now
you may have this available depending on
where you train at your local gym or
clinic somewhere
and these are machines that allow you to
test your power in a number of different
planes and this is really interesting
because companies like this are starting
to collect normative data on average
people for power testing and I don't
have anything like that to report to you
right now and so what's going to be
hopefully interesting in the coming
years is as they start to release and
publish these results I will have
normative values based on age and sex
for things that are not just vertical
jump based not all of you can do that
you may have say ankle knee or back
injuries that don't allow that or it's
not realistic or for some other reason
and so being able to identify and test
your power in things like rotation and
vertical movements that don't require
jumping and Landing are things that I
hopefully uh am able to share with you
in the coming years once those data
become available now technically the
highest power outputs seen in the
literature come from weightlifting or
what's more effectively known as Olympic
weightlifting so both the athletes
themselves as well as the movements so
the snatch clean and a jerk and
variations of this produce extraordinary
amounts of power the problem is if
you're not extremely technically
sufficient in these activities you can't
really test your power with them because
you'll be limited so much by your
Technique we won't get a true expression
of your power so if you're familiar with
those movements they are a fantastic way
to globally test your power if not you
might want to opt for something more
like that vertical or broad jump test so
to round us out here let's talk about
strength there's a lot of different
things I could pull up here but the most
direct plain measure of absolute
strength comes from the sport of
powerlifting now not to be confused with
Olympic lifting this is the sport of a
one repetition maximum in the deadlift
bench press and back squat there's a lot
of different federations and rules and
all that and so to not bog down in
unnecessary information I'm going to
give you the numbers that represent
What's called the equipped category
which is to say the highest amount of
equipment possible what's just the most
amount somebody's ever lifted there are
subcategories like raw which says you
can't have certain equipment like belts
and wraps and straps and special shirts
and things like that you could debate
whether or not you find one more
relevant or interesting than the other
one I don't really care I just want to
share with you the most amount ever
lifted any human without some arbitrary
rule that these organizations have set
now in powerlifting you get to find your
one repetition maximum among those three
exercises you can also combine them
together to get a total so from the
men's perspective there have only been
two ever
to cross the 3,000 lb barrier such that
between the three exercises squat
deadlift and bench they totaled more
than 3,000 lb the two gentlemen Donnie
Thompson and Dave Hoff Hoff having the
current world record at
3,13 PBS now my longtime friend AJ
Roberts um actually might have a better
resume here he totaled
2,855 lbs but did it at probably 30 or
50 or so pounds lower than these other
two gentlemen I'll let them I'll figure
that out but nonetheless almost 3,000 lb
across three different
exercises if you want to go through the
exercises individually we have different
people with World Records there so the
squat right now current world record is
from Nathan Baptist at an astounding
1311 lb again friends you heard that
right this is a 1300 lb back squat from
the bench press uh was this was actually
just recently broken Jimmy colb did this
and this is this is unbelievable uh the
world record is now 1350 lbs the
previous world record he broke by almost
200 lbs uh I don't know if this is more
impressive than the Usain Bolt but hard
to argue when you beat a world record by
an additional 200 lb it's like simply
unbelievable that strength
accomplishment another actually fun
thing to note here is I believe fifth or
sixth on that list is a gentleman named
Bill Gillespie at a total of
1129b he actually also did this pretty
recently and the fun part about Bill is
two things one he's 62 years old you
heard that right 62 years old and just I
think last year bench pressed well over
1100 pounds the other thing interesting
about Bill is he was actually one of my
first mentors When I Was An
undergraduate student bill was the head
strength conditioning coach at the
University of Washington I'm from that
area and so I was fortunate enough to
beg Bill to let me come up and Shadow
him one day and he said fine you can do
that but I'm training and so I showed up
there probably 30 minutes late was
beyond
embarrassed thought don't even go in go
home this is so ridiculous that you
showed up this late for a guy like that
he was the kindest sweetest guy ever put
in his mouthpiece had his training logs
out there and proceeded to do one of the
most impressive training sessions I've
ever seen while giving me guidance of
being a strength conditioning coach I'll
also never forget Bill looked at me now
context you can imagine what Bill looks
like at the time myself I'm 5'8 probably
180 PBS at the time college football
player but still incredibly small
compared to him and I will never forget
the words he said to me it made a huge
impact on my life I asked him about
being a Collegiate strength conditioning
coach as I thought this is what I wanted
to do with my life and he looked at me
straightly and directly and said you're
a dime a dozen you don't matter and he
didn't say it with hate or hurt at all
it was the kindest most direct and
helpful thing I've ever heard it changed
the trajectory in my life and it made me
realize if I wanted to make it as a
strength editioning coach I was going to
have to do a lot more than to just show
up with my exercise science degree the
third and final exercise to deadlift was
set by the famous Andy Bolton who I
believe is the only person still to this
day to ever deadlift more than 1,000
pounds at
1,08 now from the female side of the
equation you have some equally
impressive if not more impressive
numbers the world record total uh there
has only been two women ever to cross
the 2,000 lb barrier that would be Becca
Swanson and Leah rikman uh Swanson
currently owns that record at 250 pounds
the individual records the squat Leah
holds that record at 925
pounds I don't know when she's going to
cross a thousand but I keep watching to
see when it's going to happen that would
be just absolutely insane to see and and
good luck to you Leah on that one the
bench press uh an Miller currently holds
that record at 650 lb and then the
deadlift is currently set by Becca
Swanson at 694 lb so now that you know
what that gold standard really is for
strength what are some more realistic
numbers for the average person for men I
like to see about a one:1 ratio for the
bench press such that you should be able
to bench press your body weight so a 200
lb person should be aiming for something
like 200 lb bench press for women it's
about6 upper body strength is
significantly less and women in general
and so you're going to have to scale
that down a little bit more now for the
back squat it's hard to give you numbers
because it is so technically demanding I
think it's easier to give you something
more like a leg press value for men you
want to shoot for something like double
body weight and for women something like
one and a half times or so so that
hopefully gives you a little bit of
context uh of the numbers to go after
last thing I want to add here is
actually something we'll talk about a
lot more in the future and that is grip
strength is incredibly important and a
great insight into your overall health
for both athletes and non-athletes
easy to test there's a number of ways
that you can grab hand grip dynamometers
they are cheap and available almost
anywhere for men just again a rough
number here I'd like to see individuals
over 45 kilograms and then for women
over 28 kilograms or so another thing to
keep in mind here is asymmetry really
matters now this is the first test I've
given you where you can isolate you know
your left side from your right side
really important to test your grip
strength in both recent papers have come
out suggesting that an asymmetry of more
than 10% specifically increases your
risks of sarcopenia and heighten
denervation of muscle groups by 2.67
fold and so we'll talk about that more
in detail later but really really
important you want to understand whether
or not you have major asymmetries and
strength between both your sides again
some asymmetries probably okay maybe
even advantageous for some sporting
applications but asymmetries outside of
that are potentially concerning if
you're unfamiliar with that term
sarcopenia describes the the excessive
loss of muscle mass with age we know
there's going to be some sort of natural
decline in the amount of muscle mass you
have in fact on rough average men will
lose about 40% of their muscle mass from
the ages of 25 to 80 so we know it's
going to happen we've talked about how
strength training and our adequate
nutrition can reduce that loss of muscle
but some of it's going to happen so
sarcopenia really refers to the
excessive or additional loss of muscle
beyond the normal loss with aging so
those strength standards I gave you are
rough guidelines but I want you to get
as strong as possible I don't
necessarily need you to be squatting or
benching 1300 lbs but I don't want you
to just stop at body weight either so
outside of of course leading to injury
and getting hurt which is something we
don't want to do there's no disadvantage
vage to getting stronger I tried to make
that argument with muscle mass earlier
in the show but I can really make that
heavily with strength in fact if you
were to compare the two muscle mass to
muscle strength muscle strength is by
far a stronger predictor of both how
long you're going to live as well as how
well you will live within those years
that's number one number two getting
stronger only continues to reduce your
risk of developing things like
sarcopenia or late on set dementia in
fact one particular study of note here
this study had around 500,000 or so
individuals pulled from the UK biobank
which is a similar setup as what we've
got here in America that I talked about
earlier in our n Hayes database now they
studied these individuals across nine
years and during that time around 4,000
or so of the individuals developed
dementia and so what's interesting is
they're able to go back and say okay
what unique characteristics existed
prior to the dementia as well as after
the onset
and how did that compare to the
individuals who didn't have the diena
set in and in this one certain study in
just one study so we want to be cautious
of over interpreting here what they
found was
30% of the dementia cases were
attributed to having low grip strength
and this was independent of a number of
other important confounders we will talk
about these things more in future
episodes and I don't want you to get
overly concerned with that specific
result or those specific numbers
I just wanted to highlight though the
critical importance of getting stronger
really helps overall Global health and
what's furthermore interesting about
this paper and many many many others is
there doesn't seem to be an upper limit
so when you continue to increase
strength you continue to reduce risk of
all cause mortality dementia and similar
other things and so we don't see this
really even an ASM toote we don't see a
tapering off of benefit we just continue
to see Rises and improvements in Risk
reduction factors um Hazard risk
mortality risk a number of other things
important to overall health when we
continue to get stronger whether we're
talking about grip strength leg strength
or anything else and so it just right
now according to the data across again
multiple areas just continuing to get
stronger seem to continually benefit
human health and performance at this
point we can now move into our final eye
which is intervene in other words what
do you do to improve your muscle quality
I'm going to give you four big areas to
focus on the very first one is similar
to what we talked about for muscle
quantity and that is you want to train
all of your joints through all their
ranges of motion one thing people fail
to realize is it's good to be strong but
you need to be strong and fast and have
good endurance over the entire range of
the motion you're going to be put into
positions likely where the muscle needs
to contract when it's shortened when
it's extended and many other positions
and so we want to train that somehow
across multiple range of motion the
first first is similar to what we talked
about with muscle quantity and that is
all ranges emotion you want to be strong
fast and have great endurance when your
muscles are both shortened when they're
extended and when they're in various
positions as always we don't ever want
to put a joint into a bad position and
then we definitely don't want to load
that or contract that but as much as we
can we want to force human movement in a
high quality through a large range of
motion the second one here is being
intentional so where this differs than
say the muscle size issue is muscle
quality is about eliciting an
improvement in human movement whether
this means we're more efficient whether
we're producing more power or speed
we've got to move in a certain way and
so now we're talking about a quality
that extends outside of the muscle
itself and into a human movement and so
we want to be incredibly intentional
about how we're moving our technique our
Rhythm our timing our Tempo what should
be moving what should be relaxed what
should be contracting is all critically
important to moving better if you ask
any sprinting coach they're going to
talk about things like Rhythm and timing
and Tempo and what they're really
talking about is this stuff how this
applies to everyone else is simply
understanding when I'm trying to
contract say my pecs or my shoulders for
a bench press what should my glutes be
doing should they be contracted all the
way should they be totally off and
relaxed should they be halfway things
like that so paying attention to your
movement quality is the fastest way for
most people to actually move faster and
move stronger improve technique first
and then chase after improving maximal
capacity of the actual muscle fiber and
tissue the third is in making sure
you're balancing movement planes and
posture so if you want to get a better
squat make sure that your glutes aren't
significantly stronger than your
hamstrings or that your adductors your
you're groin and the muscles that kind
of pull your knees together aren't
significantly weaker you will only ever
be as strong and as fast as your weakest
link in that movement chain so ensuring
you don't have anything grossly behind
something else and that you're training
yourself so that the muscles move
appropriately think about it this way
there are some muscles and joints that
are meant to be stable and others that
are meant to be movers and they tend to
stack in an every other one fashion such
as this I gave the examples of the knee
and the hip earlier the ankle is to be
highly mobile and to move a lot the knee
is meant to be stable so if the knee is
stable this allows the ankle to move a
lot and then the opposite direction
would be the hip so you want a highly
mobile hip a highly stable knee so you
can have a highly mobile foot going
above that since the hips are mobile you
want the low back and the lumbar spine
to be stable so that the thoracic and
kind of midback spine can be mobile so
that your shoulder joints and your neck
can be stable this allows then the
shoulders to be mobile the elbows to be
stable and the wrist to be nice and
mobile now it is more complicated than
that but really at the highest level
that is a a nice summary of how the
muscle actions are supposed to work if
you think about that in general context
it's going to keep you pretty safe and
it's going to allow you to move well
lastly then is what I call the 3 to five
rule so the three to five rule applies
to strength power and speed whatever
roughly means is this choose three to
five exercises do three to five
repetitions for three to five sets rest
for 3 to 5 minutes in between each set
and repeat that three to five times per
week so at the lowest level this could
mean three sets of three repetitions
three days a week of three exercises
this would be a pretty low volume but
because of that that would allow you to
go really really heavy or to really high
intensity you're going to have a lot of
recovery not going to stimulate a lot of
muscle growth won't stimulate hardly any
muscular endurance but could be used if
you're trying to maximize the
recoverability or the strength aspect
going higher on that Spectrum say five
sets of five of five exercises five days
a week would get closer to the
hypertrophy or muscle growth into the
Spectrum would give you a little bit
more muscular endurance and would be a
lot more volume for those individuals
for higher training status for muscular
endurance you can add any number of
things uh more repetitions per set um
more sets less recovery in between sets
or anything else like that training to a
little bit of fatigue is a pretty easy
way to think about muscular dirs of
course exercise science is an entire
scientific field it gets far more
complicated than that but that is a
rough idea of how to intervene to change
the quality of contraction of which your
muscles can go through so to wrap
everything up today we talked a lot
about skeletal muscle mus we went over
how it actually works what it's made of
why in my opinion it is the most
important organ in the entire body and
deserves more credit and attention we
talked about why you want to make sure
that it is functioning at the highest
level possible this means both a quality
of muscle functionality contractile
properties how much force it can produce
how fast it is and other things like
that as well as the quantity of it how
much muscle you have in general we went
into a little bit of the microanatomy so
the difference between fast s fibers and
slow twitch fibers and why it's
important that you pay particular
attention to high Force activities in
order to preserve those fast twitch
fibers regardless of whether or not
you're an athlete or a person interested
just in longevity and overall Wellness
so from there we talked about the three
eyes the first being investigate so
identifying whether or not you have
enough muscle and how it's functioning
in terms of power and speed and so on
the next eye of course was
interpretation so letting you know
whether the amount amount of muscle and
the strength and power you have is good
great close to some of our world records
whether you're male or female or maybe
not quite as high as you think and then
lastly to intervene so what do you do
about it what are some protocols and
things you need to do from a lifestyle
perspective to improve the both muscle
quality and quantity I hope you found
this initial discussion of skeletal
muscle interesting and useful now when I
say initial that's for a reason I have a
lot more to tell you about skeleton
muscle but we're going to have to save
that for future episodes thank you for
joining for today's episode our goal is
to share exciting scientific Insight
that helps you perform at your absolute
best if the show resonates with you and
you want to help ensure this information
remains free and accessible to anyone in
the world there are a few ways that you
can support first you can subscribe to
the show on YouTube Spotify and apple
and on Apple and Spotify you can leave
up to a five-star review given that
we're a new podcast subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot second please check out our sponsors
the show would not exist without them
and they really are exceptional products
and services and then finally you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it if you have any
content questions or suggestions please
put those in the comment section on
YouTube I really do try to read these
and see what you have to say I use my
Instagram and Twitter also exclusively
for scientific communication so those
are great places to follow along for
more learning my handle is Dr Andy gal
on both platforms thank you for
listening and never forget in the famous
words of Bill Bowerman if you have a
body you're an athlete